https://www.orangutans-sos.org/privacy-policy/

Privacy Policy
The processing of your personal data is carried out by or on behalf of Sumatran Orangutan Society
Sumatran Orangutan Society is a registered charity in England and Wales (1158711)
HOW CAN YOU CONTACT US?
If you have any questions or concerns regarding our Privacy Policy or our processing of your personal information, please contact:
OX14 5BJ
Email: info@orangutans-sos.org or contact by telephone at 01235 530825(or 00 44 1235 530825 if you are calling from outside the UK).
NOTIFICATION OF CHANGE OF PRIVACY & COOKIE POLICY
This Privacy & Cookie Policy may change from time to time. Please visit this website section periodically in order to keep up to date with the changes in our Privacy Policy.
COOKIE CONSENT
By using our website, our social media pages (such as Facebook, Twitter, YouTube and Instagram), subscribing to our services, donating to us and/or shopping online, you agree that, unless you have set your computer’s browser to reject them, we can place the types of cookies set out below on your device and use that data in accordance with this policy.
PRIVACY POLICY
HOW DO WE COLLECT YOUR INFORMATION?
We may collect information about you directly whenever you interact with us. For example, when you contact Sumatran Orangutan Society regarding our activities, register as a supporter, send or receive information, engage with our social media or make a donation to us, you may provide us with your personal information.
We may also receive information about you when you interact with third parties with whom we work. For example, where you’ve made a donation to us through a third-party website (e.g. Just Giving or Virgin Money Giving) and given them permission to share your information with us.
We may supplement what we know about you with information that is available to the public. For example, in order to ensure that our communication with you is relevant and tailored to your  interests, we may collect information about you from publicly-available sources either directly or through third-party subscription services or service providers. See ‘How will we combine and analyse the information we collect about you?’
We may collect aggregated or anonymous information when you visit our website or interact with our content. For example, we may collect information about the services you use and how you use them, like when you watch a video on YouTube, visit our website or view and interact with our ads and content.  Please see our Cookie Policy for more detail.
WHAT INFORMATION DO WE COLLECT?
The information we collect from you directly or from third parties with whom we work, may include:
name
address
email address
telephone number
contact preferences
bank account details for setting up a regular direct debit
credit card details for processing credit card payments
employer details for processing a payroll gift
taxpayer status for claiming Gift Aid, and
date of birth, age, and/or gender, where appropriate (e.g. where registering for an event, such as an information evening or a race).
We do not use cookies to collect this type of information. All online financial transactions will be encrypted using TLS (Transport Layer Security).
We may also collect and process information about your interactions with us, including details about our contacts with you through email, post, on the phone, through social media or in person (i.e. the date, time, and method of contact), details about donations you make to us, events or activities that you register for or attend and any other support you provide to us.  We may also collect and record any other relevant information you share with us about yourself, including your interests or your affiliations with other charities, community groups, your employer or a Sumatran Orangutan Society corporate partner. If you are a minor, we may collect the name and contact details of a parent or guardian and, where appropriate, the name and location of your school.
In order to ensure that our communication with you is relevant and tailored to your background and interests, we may supplement what we know about you with information that is available to the public.  This allows us to better understand your interests, preferences, and level of potential engagement and/or donation, so that we can contact you in the most appropriate way and to ensure that we do not send you unwanted communications.  The information we collect and process about you from publicly-available sources may include demographic information associated with your postcode or your address and an estimate of your age.  We may collect this information ourselves or through third-party service providers.  For more information on how we work with service providers, please see ‘How will we disclose the information we have collected to outside parties?’.
Where we have identified that you may have the capacity or affinity to support Sumatran Orangutan Society at a higher level, we may use the information we hold about you to identify connections between you and our existing circle of key supporters.  We may also review other information about you that is available to the public through internet searches, subscription services, or public databases (e.g., Companies House, the electoral register, or the land registry), such as information about corporate directorships, shareholdings, published biographic information, employment and earnings, philanthropic interests and networks, charitable giving history and motivations and relevant media coverage, so that we can engage with you in a more personalised way.
DO WE PROCESS ‘SENSITIVE’ PERSONAL INFORMATION?
Under data protection law, certain categories of personal information are recognised as sensitive, including health information and information regarding race, religious beliefs, and political opinions (‘sensitive personal data’).  In limited cases, we may collect sensitive personal data about you. We would only collect sensitive personal data if there is a clear reason for doing so, such as  where we need this information to ensure that we provide appropriate facilities or support to enable you to participate in an athletic event like a marathon.
HOW DO WE USE YOUR INFORMATION?
We may use your information in a number of ways, including:
To provide you with information, products or services that you have requested from us or that we feel may be of interest to you;
To provide you with information about our work or our activities;
To invite you to participate in interactive features on our website;
To process donations we may receive from you;
To fundraise in accordance with our internal policies and procedures;
For administrative purposes (for example, we may contact you regarding an event for which you have registered, to provide information requested from us or with a query regarding a donation you may have made to us);
For internal record keeping relating to any donations, feedback, or complaints;
To invite you to participate in voluntary surveys or research;
To contact you where you have been identified as a contact person for an organisation, such as a school (if we obtain your contact details in this way, we will only use them to contact you in your capacity as a representative of that organisation);
To analyse and improve the content and operation of our website;
To analyse and improve our internal business processes;
To analyse the personal information we collect about you and use publicly available information to better understand your interests, preferences and level of potential donations so that we can contact you in the most appropriate way and to ensure that we do not send you unwanted communications;
To tailor advertising that is presented to you on the Internet according to your interests, preferences and other characteristics (as described below);
To direct advertisements and other communications to other people who may have similar interests or other characteristics to yours (as described below);
To assess your personal information for the purposes of fraud prevention; and
Where we are required by law to disclose or otherwise use your information.
In particular, we may contact you for marketing purposes by email if you have agreed to be contacted in this manner.  We may also send you service communications via email, for example where you place an order for goods or services on our website, or you have made a donation.
If you have provided us with your postal address or telephone number, we may send you information about our work or other communications of the kinds described above by direct mail or contact you by telephone unless you have told us that you would prefer not to hear from us in this way.  We provide information about how you can change your marketing preferences below.
HOW WILL WE COMBINE AND ANALYSE THE INFORMATION WE COLLECT ABOUT YOU?
We are committed to communicating with you using an approach that is right for you. This means that we manage the communications we send you to ensure that we are contacting you in the most appropriate way and that we are not sending you unwanted communications.  In order to do this, we may combine the information that we collect about you and analyse what we know about your interests, preferences and level of potential engagement or donation. We may also use statistical analysis to analyse this data and understand the likelihood that you will be interested in or responsive to a campaign or message. We may use third party service providers to assist us in this process.  For more information on how we work with service providers, please see ‘How will we disclose the information we have collected to outside parties?’.
Where we have identified that you have the capacity or affinity to support Sumatran Orangutan Society at a higher level, we may collect additional information about you (see ‘What information do we collect?’) and combine and analyse that information in a profile of you that will assist us in engaging with you in a more personalised way.
You can opt out of your data being combined and analysed for marketing purposes by contacting our Data Protection Officer as described below. However, this may mean that you stop receiving marketing communications from us more generally.
In accordance with our legal and regulatory obligations and our internal policies and procedures, we may also use personal information to carry out due diligence on potential or actual donors.  If you opt out of analysis of your data for due diligence purposes, we may not be able to accept donations from you.
HOW WILL WE DISCLOSE THE INFORMATION WE HAVE COLLECTED TO OUTSIDE PARTIES?
Sumatran Orangutan Society may provide your information to our service providers. Subject to your communication preferences and our internal policies and procedures, this would include providing your information to third parties that work with us to deliver on our charitable purposes, and other entities that act as fundraisers for Sumatran Orangutan Society, sell Sumatran Orangutan Society products or provide Sumatran Orangutan Society with marketing information and services.
Where you have agreed to receive email or SMS marketing communications from us, we may provide your email address or mobile phone number in an encrypted format to social media companies, such as Facebook, Instagram, Twitter or YouTube, or to digital advertising networks that are providing services to us by displaying our advertising to you on those social media platforms and other websites, as well as identifying audiences with interests similar to yours. You can opt out of your data being used to display advertising to you by contacting our Data Protection Officer as described below.  However, this will not prevent our advertisements being shown to you on a randomised basis or based on cookie data and may mean that you stop receiving marketing communications from us more generally.
We enter into contracts with all of these service providers that require them to comply with data protection laws and to ensure that they have appropriate controls in place to protect the security of your information.
We will never sell your details and, except as indicated below, will only share your details with third parties (who are not service providers working at our direction) if you ask us to.  We will not make cold telephone calls to members of the general public and, therefore, will not purchase your data in order to do so.
We may disclose your personal information if we are requested or required to do so by a regulator or law enforcement or in order to enforce or apply our rights (including in relation to our website or other applicable terms and conditions) or to protect Sumatran Orangutan Society, for example in cases of suspected fraud or defamation, or in order to comply with any other applicable legal obligation.
HOW DO WE PROTECT YOUR PERSONAL INFORMATION?
We take appropriate physical, electronic and managerial measures to ensure that we keep your information secure, accurate and up to date, and that we only keep it as long as is reasonable and necessary.
Although we use appropriate security measures once we have received your personal information, the transmission of information over the internet is never completely secure. We do our best to protect personal information, but we cannot guarantee the security of information transmitted to our website, so any transmission is at the user’s own risk. However, any payment card details (such as credit or debit cards) we receive on our website are passed securely to our payment processing provider according to the Payment Card Industry Security Standards.
For financial and technical reasons, we may, on occasion, need to use the services of a service provider outside the European Economic Area (EEA) – this may include a country which does not have the same level of data protection as in the United Kingdom.  However, unless they are located in a country which has been assessed by the European Commission as ensuring an adequate level of protection for personal data, we will only use a service provider outside the EEA on the basis of an agreement with the service provider, designed to protect your data, in the appropriate form approved for this purpose by the European Commission.  We will take all steps reasonably necessary to ensure that your data is processed securely and in accordance with this Privacy Policy.
HOW CAN YOU CHANGE YOUR MARKETING PREFERENCES OR UPDATE THE INFORMATION WE HOLD ABOUT YOU?
We pledge to make it clear and easy for you to choose how you hear from us. If you do not wish us to use your personal data for marketing purposes as outlined above, you can use the relevant box on the form on which we collect your data to indicate your preference.
You can also change any of your marketing preferences at any time (including telling us that you don’t want us to contact you for marketing purposes) by:
Indicating that you do not wish to receive our marketing emails by clicking the ‘unsubscribe’ link in at the end of our marketing emails;
Contacting us through our Supporter Care team by email at info@orangutans-sos.org, or by telephone at 01235 530825 (or 00 44 1235 530825 if you are calling from outside the UK), or by writing to us at:
Supporter Care
Sumatran Orangutan Society
6 Lombard Street,
Abingdon
Oxfordshire OX14 5BJ
Entering your details on the Fundraising Preference Service (FPS) website and choosing ‘Sumatran Orangutan Society’ (Charity Number 1158711).  This service is run by the Fundraising Regulator and allows you to stop email, telephone, addressed post, and/or text messages from a selected charity or charities by using the online service at www.fundraisingpreference.org.uk or by calling the telephone helpline on 0300 3033 517. Once you have made a request through the FPS, we will ensure that your new preferences take effect within 28 days of your request.
If you have indicated that you do not wish to be contacted for marketing purposes, we will maintain your details on a suppression list to help ensure that we do not continue to contact you for marketing purposes.  However, we may still need to contact you for administrative purposes, including (but not limited to):
Processing a donation you have made and any related Gift Aid;
Providing you with the information you need in order to participate in an activity or event for which you have registered (e.g. a marathon); and
Explaining and apologising where we have made a mistake.
Similarly, if your contact details have changed or you think any information we have about you is incorrect or incomplete, you can always update or correct the information we hold about you by contacting us through our Supporter Care team as explained above.
WHAT OTHER DATA PROTECTION RIGHTS DO YOU HAVE?
You can make a complaint or raise a concern about how we process your personal data by contacting our Data Protection Officer.  In some circumstances, you have the right to object to our processing of your personal data or to stop us from continuing to make active use of personal data that we retain in our records.
If you are not happy with how we have handled your complaint, you can contact the Office of the Information Commissioner, which oversees the protection of personal data in the UK, or the Fundraising Regulator, which is responsible for overseeing fundraising activities carried out by charities in the UK.
Alternatively, you may choose to contact either the Information Commissioner or the Fundraising Regulator directly about your complaint, regardless of whether you have raised it with us first.
You also are entitled to request a copy of the personal information relating to you which is kept on file by Sumatran Orangutan Society (for which we may charge a small fee) by contacting our Data Protection Officer.
WHY ARE WE ALLOWED TO PROCESS YOUR PERSONAL INFORMATION?
Our Privacy and Cookie Policies take into account several laws, including:
the Privacy and Electronic Communications (EC Directive) Regulations 2003
General Data Protection Regulation (EU) 2016/679
Generally, our processing of your personal information as described in this policy is allowed by these laws because we have a legitimate need to carry out the processing for the purposes described above. Some processing may also be necessary so that we can perform a contract with you or because it is required by law. We only use your information to send you marketing communications by email or text message with your consent, and you can always opt out of receipt of marketing communications by post or telephone as explained below.
JOB AND VOLUNTEER APPLICANTS AND CURRENT AND FORMER EMPLOYEES
If you apply to work at the Sumatran Orangutan Society, we will only use the information you give us to process your application and to monitor recruitment statistics. If we want to disclose information to someone outside the Sumatran Orangutan Society – for example, if we need a reference, plan to use an external supplier to run background checks or need to get a ‘disclosure’ from the Disclosure and Barring Service (DBS) – we will make sure we tell you beforehand, unless we are required to disclose this information by law.
When recruiting for a post based in another country, Sumatran Orangutan Society will sometimes need to transfer your personal information to that country to progress the recruitment. It may be that that country does not provide the same level of data protection as in the European Economic Area.
If you are unsuccessful in your job application, we will hold your personal information for 6 months after we’ve finished recruiting the post you applied for. After this date we will destroy or delete your information.
If you begin employment with us, we will put together a file about your employment. We keep the information in this file secure, and will only use it for matters that apply directly to your employment.
Once you stop working for us, we will keep this file according to our record retention guidelines. You can contact us to find out more about this.
If you apply for a job or volunteering opportunity we will also collect information so we can assess your suitability for the role.
YOUR CREDIT OR DEBIT CARD INFORMATION
If you use your credit or debit card to donate to us, buy something or make a booking online, we pass your card details securely to our payment processing partner as part of the payment process. We do this in accordance with the Payment Card Industry Security Standard , and don’t store the details on our website or databases.
CHILDREN’S DATA
When you register with us, you are stating that you are 18 years of age or over, or are a minor acting with parental consent. You agree that any information you provide to us about yourself upon registration or at any time is true. See Terms and Conditions for more information.
OTHER WEBSITES
We cannot be held responsible for the privacy of data collected by websites not owned or managed by Sumatran Orangutan Society, including those linked through our website.
EMAILS TERMS OF USE
Emails aren’t always secure, and they may be intercepted or changed after they’ve been sent. Sumatran Orangutan Society doesn’t accept liability if this happens. The contents of emails reflect their author’s views and not necessarily those of Sumatran Orangutan Society.
Please do not send Sumatran Orangutan Society any financial data through email.
The information in emails is confidential, so if you’ve received one by mistake, please delete it without copying, using, or telling anyone about its contents.
COOKIE POLICY
COOKIES AND HOW WE USE THEM
WHAT ARE COOKIES?
Cookies are text files containing small amounts of information which are downloaded to your device when you visit a website. Cookies are then sent back to the originating website on each subsequent visit, or to another website that recognises that cookie. Cookies are useful because they allow a website to recognise a user’s device and to target the content displayed to the user’s interests.
You can find more information about cookies at: www.allaboutcookies.org and www.youronlinechoices.eu for a video about cookies visit www.google.co.uk/goodtoknow/data-on-the-web/cookies
DO WE USE COOKIES?
Yes.
TYPES OF COOKIES
There are two broad types of cookies – ‘first party cookies’ and ‘third party cookies’:
First party cookies are cookies that are served directly by the website operator to your computer, and are often used to recognise your computer when it revisits that site and to remember your preferences as you browse the site. Basically, these are our cookies.
Third party cookies are served by a service provider on behalf of the website operator, and can be used by the service provider to recognise your computer when you visit other web sites. Third party cookies are most commonly used for web site analytics or advertising purposes.
In addition, cookies may be either ‘session cookies’ or ‘persistent cookies’. Your computer automatically removes session cookies once you close your browser. Persistent cookies will survive on your computer until an expiry date specified in the cookie itself, is reached. We use both session and persistent cookies.
CATEGORIES OF COOKIES WE USE
1. Strictly necessary cookies: These cookies are essential for the user to move around the website and to use its features, e.g. shopping baskets and e-billing.
2. Performance cookies: These cookies collect information about how the user makes use of the site, e.g. which pages the user visits most. These cookies do not collect information that identifies the user.
3. Functionality cookies: These cookies remember choices made by or attributes of the user and enhance the features and content you experience during your visit to our website, e.g. language, appeals visited or user’s location. This cookie is also used to remember a user’s preferences for a font size, or customisable parts of a web page.
4. Targeting or advertising cookies: These cookies collect information about the users’ browsing habits. This may also include your use of social media sites, e.g. Facebook, etc. or how you interact with our website which then shows you relevant content elsewhere on the internet. NB. These may also be used to choose the advertisements that are displayed to you on our website and other websites.
We have assessed our cookies based on the ICC Cookie Guide. The majority of our cookies fall into the first two categories. However, we also use cookies on our webpages which are in categories 3 and 4.
WHAT INFORMATION DO WE COLLECT USING COOKIES?
We may collect some, or all, of the information available from cookies when you visit our website, depending on how you use it. We monitor how people use our website so we can improve it. We collect this information anonymously.
However, you can choose to use our website anonymously without giving us any information.  Please see ‘Changing your cookie preferences’ below.
If you visit our website, we may use cookies to record information about:
the areas of the website you visit;
the amount of time you spend on the site;
whether you are new to the site, or have visited it before;
the country, region, city and/or borough associated with your IP address or device;
how you came to our website – for example, through an email link or a search engine;
the type of device and browser you use;
how you use the website and the quality of your experience – for example we may track your bandwidth when viewing videos;
how you interact with our donation and sign up forms – for example what you select as your communication preferences; and
any error messages that you receive on the site
We use cookies to track how visitors come to our site. For example, we use marketing or referring tracking codes in internet addresses (URLs) to show us whether a visitor has come to our site via a link on a referring website or in a specific piece of marketing and to give us insight into the effectiveness of our marketing. Some of this information may be used by third party cookies to target you with relevant advertising (see below).
Although not through cookies, we do measure the success of the emails we send – so we know what subject lines and stories people liked the most. We receive this information anonymously, we don’t share this information.
WEBSITE STATISTICS ANALYTICS, TESTING AND PERSONALISATION
Our website currently uses:
Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google, Inc. (“Google”). Google Analytics uses “cookies”, which (as discussed above) are text files placed on your computer, to help the website analyse how users use the site. The information generated by the cookie about your use of the website (including your IP address) will be transmitted to and stored by Google on servers in the United States. Google will use this information for the purpose of evaluating your use of the website, compiling reports on website activity for website operators and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage.
Google may also transfer this information to third parties where required to do so by law, or where such third parties process the information on Google’s behalf. Google will not associate your IP address with any other data held by Google. You may refuse the use of cookies by selecting the appropriate settings on your browser, however please note that if you do this you may not be able to use the full functionality of this website. By using this website, you consent to the processing of data about you by Google in the manner and for the purposes set out above. For more details please read Google’s Analytics overview.
You can always opt-out of Google Analytics cookies by Google’s opt-out tool.
OTHER THIRD-PARTY COOKIES
You may notice some other cookies that are not related to the Sumatran Orangutan Society’s website whilst visiting www.orangutans-sos.org. Some of our pages contain embedded content such as YouTube video, Twitter feed or Facebook likes, and you may receive cookies delivered from these websites. Sumatran Orangutan Society does not govern the publication of third-party cookies. To understand more about their cookies and privacy statements, please visit the relevant sites.
Some of our cookies will remind you about our work and how you can help after you have left the website. These are the targeting/advertising cookies we use. It is a useful tool for us to keep public awareness of our campaigns and how they can be supported.
If you do not want cookies to be stored on your PC it is possible to disable this function without affecting your navigation around the site.
CHANGING YOUR COOKIE PREFERENCES
The “Help” menu in the toolbar of most web browsers will tell you how to change your browser’s cookie settings, including how to have the browser notify you when you receive a new cookie, and how to disable cookies altogether. Below is some helpful guidance about how to make these changes.
HOW TO DISABLE COOKIES
If you are using Microsoft Internet Explorer and you wish to block Sumatran Orangutan Society’s website cookies, you can perform the following:
1. On your browser tools menu, select ‘Internet Options’
2. Click on the ‘Privacy’ tab and then on the ‘Sites’ button
3. Type into the ‘Address of website’ field: www.orangutans-sos.org
5. Click on the ‘Block’ button
6. Click on the OK button
Find out more information about blocking or deleting cookies using Microsoft Internet Explorer.
7. Other browsers:
– Firefox cookie management
– Chrome cookie management
– Safari cookie management
Find out more detailed information on disabling cookies.
Last updated: August 2020
Zac Mills
Donate
I would like to give a
Monthly
Single
donation of :
GBP £
USD $
EUR €
AUD $
CAD $
Are you in the UK?
Tick below and we will get an extra 25p out of every £1 at no extra cost to you
Can we send you emails with updates and other ways to help?
Yes
No
If you're already subscribed then ticking No here will not
unsubscribe you. There's an unsubscribe link at the bottom
of every email we send. We’ll store your details in our
secure database and never pass your email address on to
anybody else. You can read our full
privacy policy.
Donate
First Name
Last Name
Email
Phone (optional)
To claim Gift Aid we’ll need your address
Address
Town/City
Postcode
Credit or Debit card
Donate
Get SOS email updates
Name
Email
Thank you!
Thank you for caring about orangutans.
Please look out for our first message and add us to your address book, so we don't end up in spam.
Stay connected, find out how your support is making a difference, and add your voice to the urgent call to protect Sumatran orangutans and their rainforests.
If you give consent for us to contact you here, we will send you occasional emails about our work, including project information, campaigns and fundraising.
We promise not to inundate you! We’ll store your details in our secure database and never pass your email address on to anybody else. Click here for full privacy policy.
Follow us on social media
Want to save Sumatra's orangutans? Click here to find out how!
